Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos we will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 3 - Note Input
There are a two basic ways to enter notes
in MuseScore 2.0
mouse input and step input
The simplest method is to point and click
with the mouse
You want to zoom in before you try this
Click the Note Input button
click a note value
and then click in the score
But to be honest, no one is ever going to use this method for more than a note or two
It’s just too slow
So let’s just jump right in and start learning
some shortcuts
The keyboard shortcuts for note values are
shown in the table in your screen
I suggest you just remember that
5 is a quarter note (or crochet)
From there, it’s pretty easy to remember
as the numbers go up the note values get larger
and as they down, they get smaller
With just a little practice,
you’ll have all these under your fingers in no time
You can use either the numbers
on the QWERTY keyboard
or on the keypad if you have one
So now let’s enter the first measure using the shortcuts
Let’s go ahead and delete this measure first.
We just click on it and press the backspace key
Our first note is on the and of four,
but we can’t see that right now
We’ll have to break this rest up
So I’m going to click on the rest
and then type the shortcut 4
for eight note to divide it into two eighth notes
Use the arrow key to move to the and of four
and now we’re ready to enter in the first note
I’m going to type N to enter Note Input mode
The eighth note is already selected so all
I have to do is click right there
This is a pretty simple melody and we could
continue to just enter it using the mouse
but there are better ways
Just as there are shortcuts for note values
you can also use the computer keyboard to
enter pitches by typing their letter names
Pitches will be diatonic so in this song
typing D will result in D#
Use the down arrow to change it to D natural.
Now type E, D, E
Notice that this time the D is natural
If you make a mistake,
type backspace or Cmd or Ctrl + Z for undo
The next note is tied
MuseScore will automatically add the note
on the back end of the tie
so select the note value of the second note first
in this case 6 for a half note
And now type shift = or +
MuseScore also has a virtual keyboard you
can use to choose pitches
Go to the View menu and select Piano Keyboard
or just type P
You’ll see the Middle C is indicated on
the keyboard
Select the note value
and then play the note on the keyboard
For the next note, a dotted note,
choose the base value quarter note first
Then type period to add the dot
and then click on the keyboard
Now type 4 and enter the four 8th notes
Finally type 7 for a whole note
and then shift = or + for the tied note
So now we have our first phrase
In the next video we’ll complete the melody
using some methods that are even faster